Jack: So, let’s look at
parallelisation in more detail.
Parallelisation is a method of processing
in which separate parts of an overall task
are broken up and run simultaneously on
multiple CPUs which in turn reduces the
amount of time involved in processing.
Leah: This also allows large
problems or processes to be divided
into smaller ones, which can be
run and solved at the same time.
Imagine a road which consists of
one lane, traffic will be slow, and
any blockages will cause it to stop.
Now think about a motorway with 3
lanes, slow traffic can still go slow
without holding up the faster traffic
in the other lanes and a lot more
traffic can get to the end of the
road quicker and more efficiently.
Jack: So how does this work in processing?
Let’s say, for example, that we
have a list variable of length 100
which contains numerical values,
and that we want to perform a
mathematical operation on each value.
Leah: For arguments sake, let’s say
that each computation will take 1
second and use 1mb of memory, and that
we have 20mb of RAM available to use.
If we do this in a sequential
manner, we will have to wait
for the previous computation to
finish before the next one starts.
This would then take 100 seconds to
complete this operation [number of
operations x length of time to complete
one operation: 100 x 1 second],
and process at a rate of 1mbps.
Jack: If with the process, there
are no dependencies [for example
one operation does not depend on the
outcome of a previous] we can use
parallel processing to perform multiple
operations at once and maximise the
use of the memory that is available.
With 20mb free, this means we can
process 20 x 1mb operations at a time.
Leah: This process will then take
5 seconds to complete [[number of
operations/memory available] x length
of time to complete one operation:
[100/20 mb] x 1 second] and process
at a rate of 20mbps, therefore 20
times faster than our first example
However, to ensure that
processes can be parallelized,
there are certain dependencies.
Jack: This is where pure functions
are useful for parallelisation.
If all of the parallel processes
were dependent on a global variable
that it modified, like an impure
function could, this would change the
outcome each time a process completed.
We can therefore use pure functions with
no external dependencies to ensure that a
parallel process can be computed reliably.